# RACHEL DANIEL

# SOFTWARE DEVELOPER

#### CONTACT

(615) 598-0659



in linkedin.com/in/rachel-daniel-nashville/



github.com/racheldaniel

# ABOUT ME

I love solving puzzles. There is a joy in the balance of creativity and logic that has been an undercurrent in all of my academic and professional endeavors. Having graduated with a BFA in Theater and a minor in Accounting, I knew I wanted to find a career that was as challenging as it was rewarding.

So how does a Theater major find her way into software?

In 2010, I joined Community Health Systems (CHS). There, as a Systems Operations Analyst, I had the opportunity to work closely with developers in gathering data about the system use for the department. After being promoted to Systems Operations Manager, my increased involvement in the development process sparked a passion for code-particularly for being a part of the creation and improvement of technology with an emphasis on the end user-- which culminated in leaving to attend Nashville Software School's six month Python/ Diango bootcamp. I am excited about this new journey as a software developer that brings with it the opportunity to problemsolve and learn something new each day.

# **EDUCATION**

#### **Nashville Software School**

Full-Stack Dev | Oct 2018 - Present Six Month Bootcamp for Full-Stack Web Development (back end Python/Django)

University of Mississippi

Bachelor of Fine Arts | 2006 - 2010 Theatre Arts, Minor in Accounting Sally McDonnell Barksdale Honors College Magna Cum Laude

#### EXPERIENCE

#### Nashville Software School

NSS is a Tennessee Non-Profit corporation providing intensive training, mentorship and apprenticeship in order to prepare students for an entry level software developer job creating web sites, applications and/or mobile apps.

# Full-Stack Developer | Oct 2018 - Present

Six month bootcamp covering front-end (HTML, CSS, JavaScript ES6 with React) and backend Python/Django-emphasis on team environment and Scrum methodology

- · Version Control with git/GitHub on all individual exercises and group projects
- Modular Code and Workflow Automation with Grunt and Browserify-- applied in first version of group project, Waddle
- · Group Collaboration focused on introductory industry standards-- including Sprint and project planning, white-boarding, daily stand ups, team leads, code reviews and retros
- CSS and JS Libraries, Frameworks and Package Management including React, NPM, Bootstrap, ReactStrap, Materialize and ¡Query
- SPA and CRUD Application Development
- JSON Server, Database Management and ERDs
- · SQL using SQLite for use in raw queries within Python, as well as the set up for a database
- · Python syntax, structure and unit testing
- The basics of CLI applications
- · Django's use of Models, Views and Templates, and use of ORMs for database calls

## **PROJECTS**

## GiftStorm: The Brainstorming App for Gift-Giving

NSS Front-End Capstone Project | github.com/racheldaniel/Gift-Storm

- · As someone with a large immediate family, birthdays, anniversaries and other celebrations seem to sneak up on me on a monthly basis, leaving me not only gift-less, but idea-less.
- To put an end to last-minute holiday scrambling, I created GiftStorm -- a React App that allows users to track interests, gift ideas, purchases and upcoming holidays for all of their friends in one, easy-to-use interface.
- Using a local JSON database, the app stores all user-specific data, allowing unique experiences depending on the logged-in user. The app features full CRUD functionality, so users can add, update and delete interests, ideas and purchases, as well as what holidays they are tracking, allowing the user to brainstorm freely and spontaneously.
- · GiftStorm uses Moment.js to display the closest upcoming celebrations to the user along with the status of their gift purchasing for that occasion.
- The app is simple and user-friendly, styled with ReactStrap and Bootstrap CSS frameworks.

#### Bangazon

NSS Back-End Group Project | github.com/raving-remoras/bangazon-workflow

- Bangazon is a fictitious company created by NSS in desperate need of an app for managing employees and their assigned computers, departments, and training programs.
- · Our team was provided with a series of tickets, and was responsible for Sprint planning for the 5-day project-- estimating our velocity and assigning ourselves tickets for the first milestone.
- We utilitzed Django to interact with our SQL database-- created using Django models and populated with a customized seeder file. The application uses GET and POST ORMs for full CRUD functionality, and is minimally styled using Bootstrap.
- In addition to serving the role of Team Lead for this project-- facilitating initial planning and daily check-ins before formal stand-ups-- my primary responsibility during the project were the Employee views.
- The Employee views listed employees and their respective departments, allowed the user to add new employees, and afforded the option to edit employee data-- including their assigned computer and scheduled trainings.

# PROJECTS (CONT)

#### Waddle v.1 & 2

NSS Front-End Group Projects | Waddle 2.0: github.com/penguin-sweater/react-nutshell

- Waddle is the premier social media app for literate Penguins-- based on a mock client request for an application that would allow users to post news articles, todo lists, upcoming events, and chat messages -- and see what their "friends" on the app had also posted.
- In version 1, our team utilized Grunt, ESLint and Browserify to lint, unify and compile our code-- which was modularized and written in vanilla JavaScript. We styled our first version using Materialize.
- In version 2, we refactored our code into React components with JSX. We styled using Bootstrap as well as Reactstrap elements.
- In both versions we stored data in a JSON file and used the MomentJS NPM
- •My primary responsibilities for both versions of this project include the Events page and all related components as well as the API module containing base functions for API calls. Additionally, I assisted with the Friends component of the React version, as well as the overall styling and structure of both versions.

#### **EMPLOYMENT**

# Community Health Systems | May 2009 - Sept 2018

CHS is a Fortune 500 company and provider of general hospital services in the US. My 8+ years with CHS were spent working for the Eligibility Screening Services department, which specializes in locating federal, state and/or county programs to cover the medical bills of uninsured patients of CHS hospitals.

#### Systems Operations Manager | Dec 2017 - Sept 2018

- Manage a team of six analysts who in turn handle departmental equipment distribution, technical support, security/access, reporting and data analytics
- Construct ad hoc reports for department leadership using SQL and Excel
- First point of contact for department leadership for troubleshooting in Artiva (Ontario Systems) as well as Enhancement Requests for Artiva
- Oversee the Month End Invoicing process, wherein the Ops Analysts search for system issues preventing payments from reaching Artiva, validate existing payments and make adjustments to invoices before distribution
- Attend and contribute to weekly Enhancement Meetings with the Director of Sys Ops and the Artiva Developers
- Meet regularly with the Sr Directors of Client Services, Education Manager, and Manager of Reports and Reconciliations to assess and coordinate training and development needs established by or brought to the Operations team

#### Acting Systems Operations Director | Dec 2017 - April 2018

- Oversee all day-to-day departmental operations including acquisitions, divestitures and host system conversions
- Present Artiva Enhancement requests to the department VP and other leadership for approval
- · Oversee development projects and testing new programming before weekly deployment
- Work with external vendor and hospital IT support contacts to oversee a host system conversion and several secondary A/R conversions

# Senior Operations Analyst | Jan 2015 - Dec 2017

- Provide weekly, monthly and ad hoc reports to departmental and upper corporate leadership using SQL and Excel
- Conduct monthly audits of all system and user errors that result in missed collections and improperly worked accounts -- providing management with specific training issues to go over with staff members, and Developers with possible system bugs
- Train other analysts on month-end tasks; provide training to Field Managers and Supervisors periodically on proper system use as it pertains to AR tracking.
- Conduct ad hoc audits and reports for department leadership

# Operations Analyst | Apr 2011 - Jan 2015

- · Perform monthly audits of all ESS invoices, validating claims and ensuring proper system use
- Conduct monthly Quality Assurance audits for Call Center Representatives to ensure proper use of Artiva for patient screening, federal/state program application and A/R tracking, and HIPAA compliance.
- Audit the inventory and invoices of prior vendors in order to provide the VP with month-over-month comparisons to ESS, accounting for differences in qualifying inventory and fee schedules.
- Provide Managers and Directors with Excel reports regarding account inventory, collections, system use and workflow.

# EMPLOYMENT (CONT)

# Call Center Representative | Aug 2010 - Mar 2011

- Call and screen CHS patients with no listed insurance for federal, state and local programs to cover the cost of medical expenses
- · Conduct Financial Counseling and refer patients to appropriate case worker or financial advisor
- Update patient accounts in Artiva (A/R Management Software) as well as individual hospital host systems-- including Medhost, Meditech, McKesson STAR and Pulse/DAR
- Maintain highly current knowledge of all available programs at each CHS Hospital location-- answer patient questions of qualifiers and application process as well as billing cycle.
- Peer-train newly hired team members

# Assistant to the Financial Advisor | May 2009 - Aug 2009

- · Assist Directors with monthly audits of all ESS invoices, validating claims and tracking invoice totals across facilities
- Various Excel reporting and data-entry for the Financial Advisor